hello and welcome this is active guest
room 52.1 on August 10 2023 we have
Ahmed al-said Alexandra aurobia and
Travis de cell
is going to give a presentation and
following we'll have some Reflections
and discussions so thank you all for
joining and amen to you for the
presentation
okay thanks so much for having me
um today I'm going to this to discuss
um our
um the methods that we came up to solve
new architectural search and new
Evolution problems
um the methods that are
um and Colony optimization based
Solutions
um so as the title ish is mentioning um
and Colony optimization for neural
architectural search and Revolution
um this work this work is um
collaboration between me uh my uh
previous advisor dried the cell and my
code advisor
um Dr Ora and senator
I'm currently
um an assistant professor in University
and
um North Carolina University North
Carolina Wellington
um
and moving on to the next slide
um so as an overview the things that I'm
going to discuss today I'll try to take
um give um bird ice view for what is the
revolution
um why we why why we need it and from
there I'll just try to discuss
um our methods that is and that is based
on and calling optimization which is
called end-based neural policy search or
ends for short and after that I will
discuss how we Advanced with this idea
um by um
introducing a continuous ants or cancer
control which is
um which good thread of down this
research space and replaced it with A
continuous space and after that
I'm going to also say what we did with
the three-dimension The Continuous ants
to have a back propagation free class
and later I will um discuss three of the
points that we are answering for
um future work
so
um
in the machine learning uh learn as the
structure the neural network structures
get got deeper and deeper
um people were trying to optimize the
structures to have better performance
and people and people in different
Realms or different
um problem domain
um used to
um borrow the best performing neural
architectures or structures and try to
modify a little bit uh to work for for
their problem and they tried to be to
tweak some of the pictures of the of the
structure and compare
um these different tweaks and then they
say that we found the best performing
structure but
um
to actually find an absolute
um open structure
it it would uh concerning that solution
it would be a NPR problem because to
reach that solution we they had to
um to to try all the combinations of the
different structural elements right and
this is and because we have massive
um structures in these deep neural
networks
um they could be an NPR problem because
we don't have computational uh Power or
enough time to actually
um train and test all of these
structures all these structures
constructed from these different
combinations
of construction hands so the alternative
way to do this is to actually try to do
to apply a meteoristic method
and to convert to an ear to open
solution that is much better than not
optimizing the structure or relying on a
kind of like a random search right a
random search can get us um better
performance performing neural network
but it's not going to give us
um an a mute to Optimal solution or to
converge through near to Optimum
solution
so
um
so I mean heuristic method would give us
an automated method
um and and also we can converge to new
document structure near to open solution
to this uh structural problem
um so the the way that people approached
Nas was by trying to mimic
um how optimization is done in nature
right so the first method the the first
way the thoughts are uh it was
um to trying to mimic how
um living organisms um evolve in nature
um using
um genetic based algorithm like the
Darwin kinetic evolution
and it started with a neat
um or
um it's it's a short for
um uh new Revolution uh foreign
that concept was also applied for in
most of the nas on normal motion methods
and exam is one of them tries to uh came
up with this method and it became one of
the state of the Arts uh instead of the
art methods in uh in in Nas
um so in in in in such methods we tried
to again mimic genetic evolution by
introducing new structural elements or
removing structural elements or altering
the structure through the evolution
process through the evolution iterations
and through the evolution Generations so
we can apply mutations by splitting
edges
or adding edges or display disabling
edges and this we display Edge we
disable edges will disable some
structural elements so that we don't
lose that component so that we can later
on use it kind of like um a dormant uh
Gene in a genome right so that we it can
appear in later generations not to get
rid of totally so we can in mutations I
can disable edges we can enable them
later in later generations if we found
that we want to try
um this option
um we can also add recurrent edges or
remove recall or or or enable or disable
the current edges uh we can we can split
nodes we can take some of the nodes that
in in the previous generation of um uh
and we can just uh split it to two nodes
and then take the edges uh connected to
that node and
um try to divide it between the new stat
was generated from the previous node in
the previous uh generation
uh also we can add nodes from to the
structures and the structure so all of
these are part of the mutation classes
in the genetic process
um you can also disable a note if you
don't if you want to try to just get rid
of one of the notes and disabling a node
or multiple nodes will also disable the
edges connected to that note
um beside mutations we are the other
side of
um a genetic process is to do crossovers
where we have two of the best
performance uh population uh made
together to bring an offspring and
Offspring will have
um collection of the characteristics uh
of coming from their parents
um so it will take some of the
characteristics from that parents and
other characteristics from the other
parent hoping that this will give us a
bad performing neural network uh or
platforming generation
um so the main problem
sorry
so the main problem with with
um uh genetic based algorithms is that
they start with minimal structure
like we can see there meaning that
inputs and outputs and um you starting
from the the optimization with this
minimal search space can trap the method
in a local Minima through the
optimization process so we were thinking
how to get rid of this obstacle and by
having a bigger or larger space to start
with and then we can sample some
solutions from that
um
larger space and we were looking around
and we we we we concerned end calling
optimization and and I would say why
that I'll try to introduce
um the method first so the method was
first introduced as um graphic
optimization method
um graph optimization method sorry
um it was introduced in mid 90s by
Margaret River
applied this method
um uh in on a terrible sales Mass
problem and the problem is mainly about
a travel salesman who wants to visit
number of cities in the country do you
think it's George's staff and
considering this problem if we have
different number and if the number of
cities grows then that combinate the
implementations of these numbers are
updated that we have to consider to find
the open solution
um if this number says gross then we
will end up having an npmr problem
because we did we won't have enough time
or or computational power to have this
um this compact this explosives solution
um done or this pixel step search done
so he
here from his observations
um
um to advance in nature he found that he
can apply how they Forge to find food in
nature
and um and uh and and then take this
this concept that this observation
applies in an algorithm to find the not
the optimum path that leads from uh from
one point and to visit all the cities
and in a short shortest plan
um so the methods this observation
um so this line in the comic slides will
just try to
give us a picture of how hence
um
um pourish in nature to plant food and
then how Market reggae took that concept
to apply it and uh in that Charles's
hitman's problem so
um hence
observance funds that and go out from
from their natural plant food
and
um the the in Detroit different
directions right
um and when they find food eventually
find food they will take some of that
food and then they will go back to their
nest and in the way back they will
deposit some other substance called a
pheromone
um that the so they deposit that
substance so that they communicate that
through the foods resource with others
so actually other ants do exploit this
for more other substance and when they
sense it they try they will they follow
the path that the end that the first end
took from that uh from the police was to
the nest
um hoping that they will find food at
the end of that time and and when they
actually find food at the end of the the
path they will take some of the food and
do the same thing they will deposit some
more from lawn on the same path they can
get more appealing to other ants who
take it so that they can bring more food
to the nest
so the this in this process shows us the
exploitation uh behavior of ants but
again from sometime from time to time
other ants also try to explore some
other uh full resources potential food
resources and they they kind of resist
uh following the the formal uh phrases
uh and and they try to find to go away
and find some um new food resources for
the nest
exploiters they also explorers and and
these two concepts were
um used by market the rager to kind of
like
right balance the search bit for the
better uh the better or faster path
between
um the the the the the the the the the
cities for the Trump salesman's problem
um and the third thing that they
observed also uh in Helen's Sports and
in nature is that the odors for more the
other substance the hormone also
evaporates so whenever a path to a full
resource is not appealing anymore with
the full resources are exclusive no more
ants will take that path or when they
take it and reached it and the the the
full resources that is exposed that they
will not take the same path to the
NASDAQ and they will try to wonder and
to find more new food resources and
because they not go in that path again
and not depending any form on pheromone
on that path the hormone will eventually
evaporate and disappears and and making
it less and less uh appealing for other
ants to take
so
um
[Music]
so that's what Marco Durango was looking
at when he thought of the travel
spaceman's problem
um he wanted he applied that uh for the
federal salesman's Problem by making one
agent
um try this different tasks and then uh
comparing in it through each iteration
so that agent will take a path between
the the cities right and then it will
compare it the the the the length of
that path to the previous uh experience
with other paths and if it's shorter it
will try to deposit for months on the
segments of that path and eventually he
was hoping and he was right about when
he was hoping he was hoping that it
eventually the the more
um that the total pattern the shorter
shorter segments that give the ultimate
shorter
um path
um had more info more and more from one
deposits making it more more appealing
for the agent to take it through the
iterations
so we we thought about this concept
um and we thought that it's very
appealing to apply it for a an Nas
problem because
solution was applied for uh graph
optimization problem and um neural
networks are in their sense
um Direction graphs
so we we also considered ankle
optimization because it's full torrent
decentralized and scalable and it's also
easily traceable
and and and think going back to being
decentralized uh it gave us it make it
it made it it made this uh
um method a perfect candidate for a pal
and high performance Computing uh
solution
um and so which will eventually
accelerate the optimization problem and
I will in the next I think in the next
Slide the slide after the next one I'll
discuss how we
um exploit or use this
um
characteristic of end connectivization
um to accelerate the solution uh that we
came up with or the method that we came
up with which is ants and games
so um this scheme or the scheme of ants
applying ants or end call accommodation
uh in a neural or sorry in neural neural
architecture search is depicted depicted
in or Illustrated in this um
uh flow chart so we start off with a
massive search space
um
expressed in superstructure which
expresses or um it embodies a neural
network that is so massively uh
connected meaning that each node in that
superstructure is connected with the
other nodes through edges and recurrent
edges backwards and forward and backward
current edges
and then we let a number of Agents swarm
over the structure uh from an input node
to an output node so each one of these
agents will pick an input node and then
it wanders from that node uh through the
connections the current edges and
recurrent edges
and between the nodes in between hidden
layers till it gets and picks one of the
output nodes and then we take all these
Paths of the different agents and we put
them together to format our a structural
and a neural network structure and we
take that structure and drain it and
test it
and then compare its performance to the
population of best performing in neural
networks through this performance
structures and it's better than the
worst in the population then we reward
um the path that the ants took the
agents took over uh in the
superstructure we worked with hormone
um and so that it may make these paths
appealing for later iterations through
through the evolution process or the or
the optimization process
that's if the the durated structure is
best than the worst in the population if
not if it actually was worse and then
the worst in the population then
we discard that structure or that in
your network and we don't reward any of
the path that ants took and also the
thermal evaporation will help us get rid
of the the pheromones that were
deposited on the edges that are not
giving us better and better structures
and
and again because the end colony is
decentralized we exploited this by
having
um an asynchronous solution or
asynchronous Evolution
um we had a main process that took care
of
um generating the new structures and
also updating the the population the
test performing structures and updating
the poor moon on the superstructure so
the main process will generate generate
um structures and send them to worker
processes the worker processes will
train and test the neural network on the
data that we have for the problem
and then send the results back or the
thickness of the neural network to uh
the main process and based on that
Fitness that being process will
um either discard it or
um we'll take that this Fitness and
compare it to the best performing in the
population if it's better than the worst
it will reward the path that ends took
on the superstructure by depositing
motion mode or if it's worse than the
worst in the population will just
discard it and it will keep generating
um new structures and sending them to
processes because the the training uh
which relies on that propagation uh is
the most computationally expensive part
in this process if we have a number of
worker processities that can work in
parallel uh to train and evaluate these
uh neural networks this newer new
structures we can speed up the process
right
by
training and evaluating different
structures at the same time internal in
in asynchronous pollution scheme
um this is actually
um this is an animation but it's not
working in this version of the slides
um because we're using a PDF but it's
mainly a structure where
um you'll see
um edges or connections between these
nodes
um fading and or having
darker colors based on the per month
values through the iterations so each
frame in this um
uh in this animation is kind of an
update for the pheromone value of the
the edges based on the performance of
the version of the of the neural network
that were generated by the Asians when
they swarm from the start node taking
one of the input nodes in the middle
layer and then from there going to one
of the Hidden layers in this one hidden
layer that we have here and from there
going to the output
so um that was the concept of applying
an ATO and current optimization and
um Nas and this now I'm going to talk
about the actual method that we came up
with
so it's more dramatic and more powerful
um neural detection search methods uh
more comprehensive if I can say if I may
say that
um
we we we opted to apply the method and
uh on um we require neural networks
because they tend to be potentially
larger than
um other C other or neural networks
structures because of their current
connections uh so we thought that if we
started this problem build the method or
the constant applies to any neural
network but applying it to recurrential
networks
um made it more appealing challenge to
for for
um
measuring the performance of the method
that we thought of
so this line in the coming side will
discuss the different heuristics of the
methods of ants the characteristic is
superstructured itself
um and as we as I mentioned before it
and it's a method search space and at
method as possible to be handled with
the the the machine or the hardware that
we're working on
um the superstructure consists of a
neural network that is massively
connected meaning that every node in
that structure is connected to the other
nodes they are or through edges forward
edges and recurrent edges backward
forward edges and backward Corner edges
um this simple structure that we have
here represents one of just the concept
of the superstructure that we have we
apply in in ants here we have three
input nodes uh three hidden layers each
have three nodes and one output node in
the output layer and we are just showing
one node connected to the other nodes
through edges which are the ones
represented in green
forward recurrent
sorry
um the the edges are the one in Gray and
then forward current and backward
current in the green end uh in the red
and the concept of recurrent edges
um might be a little bit confusing if we
look at it in this example because how
can an edge
um appear current coming in and out from
the same node or of the the notes in the
same time step but this structure might
make it more uh clear
um so here we have
um a structure that three is pretty much
similar to the one we saw before but
here we have three input nodes two
hidden layers there are three in layers
in chapter three nodes and then output
they have two notes
um and then we have also three time
steps the current times that t zero and
the the previous times that T minus one
the one before that T minus two
edges here are Illustrated using the the
solid black lines
um and and of course these edges are
present in the current time step that is
going to propagate through the neural
network and then the current uh
connections these ones are going to
bring information
um or provided information from the
previous time steps the previous
um uh inputs or previous uh data that
was fired to the nodes in the previous
language
and these are current edges are detected
here in red and orange the four ones are
better in in red and orange the reds are
coming from T minus one and the orange
are coming from the T minus two
and the backward current edges are the
dot lines in blue and green and um and
you can see that they are going
backwards so they cut the
go backward and to backward layers
um
but the uh but we but because they
already current we can do that because
they are they process information they
bring information that already processed
so we don't have to worry about
improgating information back through
time
or back through the structure but we can
do that if it's coming from previous
timestamp
the second heuristic and ants is that
Colony weight sharing we wanted to use
um then so instead of initial branding
initialize the weights or the synaptic
weights and generated neural networks uh
we wanted to use the the train weights
to initialize the weights of the newly
generated uh neural neural networks we
did that by Saving these neural networks
on the superstructure
uh we used the last
um equation here to do this update so we
balance between the ways that were saved
previously and the ways that we were uh
are coming from the trained or evaluated
neural networks and we also used two
Chinese to do this update we used
um a fixed parameter file or if we let
find that that was the first strategy
the second strategy was to
get Fly by applying these two equations
which relies on the performance of the
neural network that was previously
generally oh sorry the the previously
related entrance so it relies on the
performance of the neural network that
was trained and validated or tested
so if
um if it if the promise is was good then
we will let this uh the weights of that
um uh neural network to contribute to
the the to contribute more to the uh
initialization of the way so the newly
generated RNs if it's not performing
that well then why will this equation
will not allow it to contribute that
much
okay the third meta heuristic is
multiple memory cells so
um each at each node
um uh when when when when an agent or an
ant reached to a node in in the
superstructure it will do um a local
search
um to pick uh the type of the new in the
neuron or the type of the node uh from
these three different types of memory
cells so in the generated RNN
um the generation structure the nodes in
the structure is not all the same they
will be different based on the local
search that
um
that the agent will do or the end will
do at each node they reach through their
path from the input to an output in the
superstructure
yeah
the fourth majoristic is the multiple
anti species so we applied
um different species uh or came up with
different species for the ants
um the first specie was the ones that
will Traverse over the edges only the
edges so they would go only forward
through the edge at the the edges of uh
the neural network of the mass the
superstructure
and these ones are going to define the
number of nodes in the generated
structure I will also Define the types
of the nodes uh in the superstructure
and when they're done with their work
then the social or the second species is
the social ants
well Traverse between these nodes but
they will use the uh their current edges
to do the to do to move between these
nodes so they will create them the
recurrent edges for them really
generated RNA and we have two different
species for these social ants or three
two different subtypes of species one is
um the forward so for so the forward uh
social ends we these ones progress only
over the uh that poor connections they
go from the input to the output but over
only over the the for the current edges
and then the back where it kind of just
all the backwards social ants these ones
go go from the output to the input and
the Traverse over the Recon connections
and the way the reason we thought about
these different species is that we
wanted to control the tendency of the
ants to wander in uh around in the
superstructure exploiting the the the
the convoluted
um mesh of
um recurrent connections
um so we wanted to control that so we
came up with this strategy so that we
can
just Define the structure using the
explore ends and then the recurrent
connections can be defined after that
using the social answer
the fifth the fifth um meteoristic is
the regularization of uh promo statement
again we want it to
um give advanced in an incentive to
bring to bring
sparser and also well performing neural
networks
um we by just penalizing them if they
bring if they constructed um denser or
bigger structures
so we added this regularization term and
um formula that updated the hormone
value
uh and as you see the regularization
term relies on the performance the Ada
here is the performance of the neural
network and also relies on the size of
the structure
um the last the thick and last one is um
is is is jumping and jumping ends which
is we want to experiment with
if we let the ends of
um if we let the names
um jump over layers when they move
through the uh
through the the superstructure
um if we let them jump over these layers
to construct the neural networks
compared to if we restrict their
movement uh to jump one layer at a time
how would this uh end up
um performance wise if they will give us
parser and while performing uh
structures or they will or this jumping
would hurt down the performance
um by keeping us weaker uh structures
so
um
we use the time series data uh that can
belong to coal-fired power plant uh we
divided the data to have uh 7200
um records for training and testing and
here the plot shows that the data and we
can see that it's non-linear and
um and it's a cycle and um and not
seasonal so it's hard it's a hard
problem for a non-um uh neural network
solution or a regression linear
regression solution so
the input consists of 12 parameters when
we when we we were trying to predict
only one parameter the flame intensity
experiments covered all of the
heuristics of uh of ants
um giving different values for these
different parameters
um the superstructure is consist of 12
really good nodes three hidden layers
and chapter 12 notes and one one output
node in the output player
um the recurrent connections spent over
um three time steps one two and three
times steps
um until the the superstructure had 49
nodes uh 9924 edges and almost 3.5
um recurrent address so if you unroll
the structure over 30 72 time steps uh
in in that propagation through time will
have about 3.5 sorry 352
um thousand you know which about 6.5
million edges and 20 about 26 million uh
recurring edges
we in the experience we also compared
performance of ants uh using the same
data set uh we compare it to exam and
need so exam is the state of the art in
um neural texture search which is
um genetic based
um methods we also compare it to neat
because it's like a benchmark in the new
Revolution and Nas uh well we and also
we convert it to fixed structures
unoptimized structures that were one two
and three uh that had one and two and
three hidden layers and also different
types of
memory based cells
the experiments covered 1600 experiments
to cover all the combinations of
premature heuristics and the heuristics
of ants
um each one of these experiments was
repeated 10 times for uh uh for
statistical analysis
um
Illustrated well 2000 rnns for each
experiment each trained for 10 Apex
in in total and it's generated about a
dream related training and evaluating
32 million uh rnns it took a month and
well and a thousand CPUs to finish the
experiments
the results that we got showed that ends
up from of course out from the
unstructured
unstructured structures uh unstructured
uh sorry unoptimized an optimized
structures and it also outperformed uh
need
and then some of the combinations of
ants outperforming sense so exam here is
the fourth from the left
and we can see that the the mean
absolute error or some of the versions
or the combinations in health and
heuristics uh
out from the exam
so we we try to look to do some
statistical
um
study or the results we got from ants so
we tried to look at the top uh
performing neural networks coming from
in our results so we try to look at the
top 10 25 120 200 250 and 500 results
and we could look at
um the contribution of these heuristics
in this best performing uh neural
networks or structures
we found that these heuristics
contributed effectively uh in most of
these results but
the more the
the thing that was really
um
um intriguing for us or or surprise
surprise us is that
um the that we saw that that their
current connections
um disappeared in this results because
the best performing neural networks
um didn't have that much of Recon
connections
um we would that mean meant for us that
the the the memory based cells did the
job for recurrent information coming
from the previous times test but we
wanted to just to expand on this layer
but so it's on our list on discussing on
on our future investigations
uh so this is just a summary for
um the achievements of ants based on the
results that we got from our experiments
foreign
exploiting recurrent connection prove
successful because
um the the regularization
component of the organization heuristics
from uh
it may give us better results showing
here in this table
and also the jumping ants jumping ants
here gave us better performance compared
to non-trumping ions
and uh
and the realization also um also the the
the the
data
which ring strategy also proved
um effective when we if we look at it
there is also here compared to if we
don't apply uh wage hearing
okay
so ultimizing and strategies uh are
generic so the the
strategies that we use are generic
enough to apply it for any
um any problem or solution that is end
Colony based and end call optimization
based
um
the Vermont deposition uh that the
method that we came up with is also the
value it wasn't introduced in any
illustrator previously creature
um and the performance of ads compared
to the other uh Benchmark and state of
Art in the realm is also
um remarkable
so
going forward we thought that and was
did gave us a good resource but the main
drawback of ants was that the the the
creature space
um so ants worked on this massively
connected uh
uhmetically connected superstructure but
it's massive yes but it's still uh
discrete
um ants can move freely between these um
nodes and or they are forced to move
over between these notes over these uh
predefined uh connections whether they
are forged edges or the current edges
so
um we thought of removing that
continuous search uh the streets of
space and replacing it with A continuous
space
so we designed a 3D search space
uh where
um the the search bit had like layers
representing the length the time lengths
um and then ants can jump over between
these these layers to have to give us
the the recurrent connections and on
each of these um layers hence will just
give us the forward and the port sorry
the edges between the nodes and the
edges between the nodes
um so in this line in the comic slides
we'll show an example of how I move in
cans or continuous and
um or continuous ends
um so the an agent or an ant will just
start by picking up one of the layers
that will move on this is done in a
discrete fashion
and once this is done it will then
decide if it's going to do an
exploitation exploration movement and
and this
um example we decided to do an
exploration movement so it will
um decide the angle and the radius of
its next allocation on on that layer
once that's done it's going to go
forward and to that location and then
decides if it's going to do an
exploitation or if the next move will be
exploitational exploration move and this
example
exploitation move so it will try to
exploit the formal traces the Vermont
that was previously deposited by other
fans on in the search space so it will
use that sensing radius that's something
that was is previously defined through
each end and then it will
um
find the center of mass of the hormone
traces and then once it finds that it
will calculates that Center of mass of
the hormone it will consider it as in
its next location
and then it will move to that spot
and then it will decide about this if
its next move will be an exploitation
exploration move an eight and and at
each location before it's deciding if
about the type of the step if it's
exploitational circulation it will also
decide that if it's going to stay at the
same level at the same time like or jump
on uh to a next timeline
um if if the jump or the movement is on
the same level
um
um if the if the movement is on the same
level the end when if the S is doing an
exploitation movement it will only
consider that from one phrases that is
uh um ahead of it
um because it can't move backwards on
the same time like
otherwise it will be doing backwards
step which is not allowed in in your
Networks
but if it's going to
um another time lag
um above above layer then it can be it
then it's going to do a recurrent Edge
and and so current edges can go back in
time oh sorry back in the structure in
the previous slide uh layer so now
the ant can consider all the formal
traces when it's tense and radius the
ones that are ahead of it and the ones
that are behind it so in this example he
is going to consider
um in this step is going to consider all
the remote traces when it's sensing
radius could calculate the center of
mass and then consider it as its next
position and then to keep doing do you
keep doing this till it reaches to the
proximity of the output nodes and once
this is done it will consider it will
decide which time which output node it
will consider as its final position in
its path from an input to the output
and
um then other ends will do the same
and then we'll have different paths from
some inputs and some outputs and then
accounts will take these paths and then
try to convince condense
um the nodes so that we don't have so
much nodes and and that are very close
to each other so the one nodes that are
within certain proximity will be uh
clustered together using DB scan
um to have less number of nodes and then
the path will be the paths will be taken
to
collected and put in a structure
a new enough structure and um then sent
to a worker process to train and test
and then compare it to the population
the best performing RNs and the plus
will be almost the same from this point
will be almost the same as ants once the
structure is constructed and the
training and testing process
will be the same as the ones that we
discussed in dance
um so this is this was also an animation
which show which shows the the how these
paths are taken by the ants uh look uh
from an input to an output in the 3D
space
it's 3D search space
so as if we look at ends uh the ants
have uh only eight uh tunable hyper
parameters compared to When comparing
this to ends and exam it's half of the
number of hyperplanners and other
methods these hyper parameters are the
number of ways layers of the search
space the number of kind of legs how
much how many of them we have in search
space number of Agents number of ants
which is similar to what we similar we
have a similar uh hyper parameter and
ants
um
the the sensing radius of the agents or
the ants
um and the agent's probability to create
a new node uh which uh represents the
exploration instead of exploitation of
the parameters or all that from one uh
back traces in the industries
um node compensation
um parameters or uh uh factors that the
the the the
the variables that are represented in
the DB scan are considered also a hyper
parameter hyper parameters and um in
cancer
um for one updating parameter and from
one volatility primer and these are also
present in
um and and SEO based problems uh
solution sorry
um the experiments used three times
years
um different number of parameters and
different sizes
um the results showed that hence
um
the results that we got from cans were
very uh competing with
um ants out and exam
um they weren't necessarily
um better but they competed they were
the same level
um but it also uh did not didn't do very
well uh on one of the database their
data sets but it's uh comparing the that
was comparing the performance of as the
main absolute error but uh comparing
cancer results uh from
um
the
sorry
uh from the size of the new networks
that we got from from Cairns we saw that
case our structures were
um sparser
it so the performance was competing with
uh hence and exam but the structures
were also were compared compared to ants
were much uh sparser uh similar to Sam
uh the the size of the structure that
we're getting from exam remember exam is
um genetic based meaning that the start
the structure the struct optimization
process using the minimal structure
elements
um but it was susceptible to it was
susceptible to local Minimus
trap traps
um and tense is not suitable to this
problem but it also gave us
um smaller structures and with
performances that we're competing with
other message examinants
so the the advantages of cancer is that
it's it has an unbalancer space compared
to ants
um result results compared uh the
results that came out were good compared
to ants and exam hyper parameters the
tunable hyper parameters are half of the
of these in examine ants
um and also indirectly encoded the
neural topology to 3D search space so
this is one of them
maybe the contributions of important
contributions depends
um then so so far aims and cans are
solutions
um that applied neural
gold architecture search meaning that
they did not
optimize the synaptic parameters of the
neural networks during the optimization
process or during the evolution process
so
um we thought we thought of actually
making ends capable of doing this as
well so to train the neural network or
optimize the synaptic weights uh the
weights of the structure of the neural
networks during the optimization process
the structural optimization process so
we added a fourth dimension to the
search space
which we embedded in uh embedded the
weights of synaptic parameters
um in in that map this terminals in that
new dimension
we also uh wanted at the ends to be
self-aware and try to
evolve
themselves through them the the
evolution process so that they can
um adapt to the changes or like um adapt
themselves so that they can give us
better performance
um the the we want them to change their
behavior of their characteristics like
the sensing radius uh they had before
for example they can be a variable that
can be can change through the iteration
thing evolve through decorations
um each end can change their uh these
characteristics uh as they are as the
evolution goes on
progress based on the performance of the
neural networks that they are generating
so um the the advantage of doing this
was that it eliminated the back
propagation process which is the most
compilation completely expensive part in
the evolution process and in the Pro in
the in the in the method that we use so
far in the exam ends and cans
um so eliminating that that propagation
gave us much much faster
Revolution process
there is also got
um I will discuss the graph on the right
hand side first which discusses the
thickness or damage meaningful error of
the results we got from
um
back propagation free cancer the four
dimension cans compared to the the
normal chance the back propagation cans
and um ends
um so the results showed us that
and again on a particular database
um that that propagation uh canes and
that propagation free chance
um did a quite a similar job
um and but they were both better than
ants on this particular database
um but they actually main contribution
or the main advantage of applying case
it shows up in the graph on the left
hand side because we can see that if you
compare the results
um based on the time of the evolution
that based on the evolution time we see
that
um hence with much had they took much
much less time than the back propagation
version of cans and uh the ants
using these different
um
um and number of amps
also this graph shows how fast and that
propagation pre-cance compared to the
normal cans
um we could so in this figure the Curves
in the data lines are shows the time
um that back propagation free cans and
cans took to prepare or generate the
neural networks or we can see that that
propagation free cans took more time
uh to prepare or generate neural
networks compared to Mac propagation
cancer the normal case and that's
because it has the fourth dimension also
has to revolve the ends of the agents
through the iteration so it needs more
time to do that
um but
um the other curve the other two curves
thing in dashed lines here are the lines
that shows the the time the amount of
time it took for the two methods to
validate much
um train and validate the neural
networks
so Mac propagation free cans doesn't
have to train the neural network doesn't
do
um uh that propagation
so it you can see that at the time it
took is in an order of magnitude less
than
um the back propagation version of
cancer
and that's these solid lines shows the
cumulative time took for both methods
and of course it shows that that
propagation precances took much much
less time than
um the back propagation three cans took
much less time
then the back propagation cancels
um the future directions that we're just
in the future points that we're
concerning for uh
sorry the point that we're considering
for future work are to turn in against
to a complete continuous space so um as
you saw
um we we the the the third the search
space for cans is not purely
um uh continuous because the time next
are represented by discrete layers uh we
want to replace this with the continuous
Dimension continuous
um layer representing the lag uh the
time lag in in rnns however this is a
little bit challenging because the num
the time length has to be uh known prior
to uh any optimization process because
um other than that we we we will be in
mapping the whole uh we the whole time
series uh as um time lapse and then
picking the time next from them which is
not
um feasible so
this is the first thing we the first
point we're considering to investigate
for in future work the second one is to
um investigate this finding that we
found we we have we found in in in in
the results
um in ants where the recurrent
connections disappear from the best
performing uh structures
um and the theory that we have is that
the memory based cells replace these
connections to give us the information
that we need from the past 9 steps
um so that they were more effective uh
more efficient in doing this compared to
their connections so we have to do this
get expand on this and investigated more
um the last thing we want to consider
also mean this is one of the top things
that we want just these three points on
the wall the top on our list
um the third one is to
actually
um you consider one of the the concept
that was coined in a book by Dr Deborah
Gordon
um which we where she mentioned that
um the living
um organism in in ant's world is not are
not the age themselves but there are the
colonies the colonies are are the
organisms that are
um the the the start and they grow and
and they interact with the environment
of the ecosystem they interact with them
with other colonies and they die at some
point and the so the ants themselves are
not organized they are the cells of
these organisms The Colony organisms so
we want to take that concept and apply
it in our methods to have a number of
colonies living together in parallel
evolving and communicating with each
other so that we and we want to see if
this will give us a better performance
but because after all we're trying to
mimic nature in our in this in in the
solution we we we're trying to
investigate
um so with this
um I'm done with my presentation and if
you have any questions
foreign
awesome wow
what a great presentation
how about you Travis and Alexander
either of you which want to go first
please feel free to give an introduction
and any primary remarks that you have on
that
okay I can say something I don't have
too much to add I think I'll go around
and did a pretty good job you know going
over the core bits of the work
um I'm Alex rorbia I'm an assistant
professor in computer science uh in
affiliate faculty affiliate professor in
Psychology and affiliate faculty in
computational neuroscience at the
Rochester Institute of Technology and I
work on a lot of stuff but rain
primarily predictive coding active
inference variational free energy a lot
of the stuff that's actually of interest
to this group and uh uh yeah and this
was a particularly interesting project
for me because a branch of my own
research is working in
neuro-evolutionary methods or even just
nature inspired meta heuristic
optimization and uh you know when I got
the pleasure of working with Abdul
Rahman when he was a PhD student at RIT
you know we you know we talked a lot
about uh the and colony-based
optimization approaches and I encouraged
him and to do to look into sort of like
the origins and also I try to understand
actually how physical ants behave so
that was always fascinating to me
um I don't have too much to edit in
terms of the technical Parts I think he
covered all the core results the only
thing I I like to think about and I'm
actually more fascinated to to hear from
the active infants Institute their
interest in the and Colony methods and
particularly what was interesting to
them because uh thinking about what does
and calling optimization how do you view
it from like an active inference
perspective is I think particularly
interesting and thinking and I even had
a thought I don't know if this was a
question among the audience's mine do
the little ant agents or the can't
agents that I'll build around and
described earlier
um you know what is there a way to start
to view them as like a multi-agent
system that's optimizing some
variational free energy quantity uh and
you know because you know a lot of even
like Carl's work I mean I collaborate
with him you know sort of touches into
this area of like well what happens with
collective intelligence and societal
organization and you can kind of look
look at free energy from these very very
high level viewpoints all the way down
to fine-grained Cellular activity and so
I'm actually more curious to know when
Daniel and anyone else in the active
entrances who can sort of explain
they're particularly interested in and
based optimization and meta heuristic
optimization I'm curious to know that
but there could be some interesting
viewpoints of you know like what is the
the free energy I think the ants
themselves are very simple I mean we
have made them more intelligent I know
of the Roman and I talked at length
about well what if we even made them for
example have like a reinforcement
learning control system and you could
even imagine well now what if the cans
themselves uh you know engage in a form
of active inference themselves what
would that look like for the system and
they are optimizing their own free
energy those are just fun little thought
experiments I we have obviously not
worked on them uh at least Abdul Rahman
was never exposed by me to that part of
my world uh in you know and biomimetic
intelligence so those are my comments
I'm not sure if they're particularly
helpful but they're very general uh and
actually more curious to know from the
active inference Institute uh their
interest in it and you know where does
that maybe perhaps intersect or is it
just like oh we like you know
interesting topics and intelligence and
so yeah
thank you Alexandra Travis you want to
say hello and give any Reflections on
The Talk
we're all coming hope somebody can see
me a little bit
in White Jungle here I'm hi I'm Travis's
cell I'm an associate professor at RIT
I'm also also the graduate program
director for a master's in data science
so if any of you are interested in any
of this or data science please you know
shoot me an email
um you know I thought this work was
really very interesting in a lot of ways
so a lot of Dollarama was working on it
um I think one of the coolest Parts
about it is a popular neuro Evolution
algorithm
um that came after me is called
hyperneat and it transforms the
um discrete search space of neural
architecture search into a continuous
one
um and it's it's shown to be pretty a
pretty powerful method well this this
version of ant colony optimization the
new one does the same thing that makes
the search space continuous but what I
found was really cool about it was that
um as opposed to traditional ant colony
optimization where you have a graph and
you just send the amps along the edges
of the graph and you can and you take
the best paths and construct a graph
after it um here the answer actually
working like ants in the real world will
move a continuous amount of space not
just from point A to point B
um and actually dropping down pheromones
and it's more like a real simulation of
how ants would move around in the real
world
um and we're getting better results from
it than some of the old older methods so
um I think that is that really made me
be kind of happy to see that and thought
it made it as a very very interesting
work
that's awesome um Ahmed want to add
anything or I'm happy to give a thought
on the ants and ask some questions from
the live chat
oh I'm good
um trying to think covered all of the
things that we I wanted to say
um about uh um I think just one thing
that Alex mentioned that we give higher
intelligence to the agent is something
that we discussed and I'm pretty much uh
open to that I've started actually to
think about it but they didn't Implement
anything yet however the the last thing
that I discussed in the future
directions is something that I actually
started working on but they didn't start
the experiment patients yeah so
hopefully we will see something out of
that
awesome well there's a ton of ways to go
and isn't that kind of one of the
fundamental questions like in an
interactive setting either pure agent
stigmergy interaction or multi-agent but
ultimately mediated through multiple
stigma G's with like reading and writing
and error correcting codes so in that
communication setting
um I felt like the work
generalizes along multiple Dimensions
that previously approaches to
multi-aging just didn't have those kinds
of flexibilities like the continuous
time feature and and several other
features and
um
I guess with respect to the ants
themselves
um I did five Summers of field work with
ants in the USA Southwest in Arizona
and observed a lot of foraging activity
so
fat problem or that context or setting
is really a fun one and a pervasive one
across any kind of living system
anything that's going to be active
and uh living so
why did you pursue foraging type
algorithms overall and does this class
include the interaction based methods
with direct agent contacts that
Professor Gordon highlights in the ant
encounters
yeah I I wouldn't try to respond to this
but I I just learned to act to mention
that the British thought about this map
actually Travis started this idea about
using and quantumization in your version
our new architecture search by applying
this method in simpler neural networks
uh Elma and Gordon neural networks your
Cardinal networks and I did believe from
there and started working on my pieces
my my patient pieces so uh we thought
about this idea I think I I mentioned a
little bit about why we used uh and
quantumization in previous slide but
just repeating that for the audience to
make sure that I the God we thought
about this idea because
um anytimization was applied for uh as a
graph this uh a graph optimization
solution and we thought that why not and
why not your networks since they are in
business uh neural networks they are
directed so they are directed grants are
directed perhaps because the the flow of
information goes from one direction to
another Direction so that direction but
they also graph because they are nodes
connected with address and our ultimate
aim or goal is was to optimize the
structure by removing and adding
elements States so that it gives us
better performance
okay
awesome and and what one way that
Professor Gordon and others have have
talked about that bi-directional uh
learning relationship between the
computer science and the math and the
analytical formulations and then the the
field work and the actual behavior is
because the thousands of species of ants
they're working amidst a huge range of
ecologies with all these different
patterns of regularities all these
different resource distributions and
foraging it's amazing how General it is
yet it's also just one of the
functionalities that need to occur in
terms of these like even slower
processes like allocation of tissue to
faster processes even of like response
to alarm pheromone so it's like this one
class of algorithms
clearly scales across from view
ultimately one some of these foraging
algorithms are law enforesters they
don't leave Fairmont Trails so it's like
even the idea of leaving a single
positive pheromone or leaving then but
also there's things models can do that
ants can't do like the time travel
pheromone lossless perception High
dimensional uh signaling profiles that
can't occur just with like finite
amounts of molecules and
um now they are just persisting on their
path as active agents within one
generation with a variational free
energy at the behavioral scale and then
across generations with that
evolutionary layer and the relationships
between the neural network
implementation and the active inference
model they're kind of like two ways of
describing slash implementing
um yeah I'd be curious to hear any of
your thoughts on where you see active
inference coming into play or how do you
see old ultimately similarities and
differences between neural network-based
approaches and active inference-based
approaches are they same complementary
overlapping
you guys want to stick this one
I think this might be more of an Alex
question to be honest
well yeah I mean if you want to keep it
on active inference but I think Travis
you're going to need to tag in when you
want to get into the very specifics of
like the actual and Colony details
because again I kind of see Dan Colony
optimization from a more global point of
view I would say
so to be clear I mean this particular
work that I'll be so that way of the ram
is not also completely blindsided by
your question Daniel even though the
name is in the Institute itself uh this
isn't an active inference work so you
know again while there are obviously as
you pointed out lots of interesting
elements like for example the fact that
the ants when they conduct their
exploration along let's just think about
like the recurring networks and they're
figuring out what nodes and what as
uh explain the superstructure right as
they iterate across with the pheromone
trails and figure out what nodes I want
to recurrently connect be forward
connect skip connect so on and so forth
um you you would say well okay what
these ants are doing is they're engaging
in epistemic foraging which is a key
Concept in active inference or idid so
that way I'll build Ramen and Travis are
not also left behind by jargon uh Epi
Summit forging in active inference it's
a big General framework it's like a
biological neurobiological process to RL
and epistemic just refers to kind of
like the uncertainty Travis that you and
I work on and the ideas it's saying well
okay I want to understand my world and
the more that I explore my world right
there will be things that surprise me
less but if I encounter some information
that is really weird when I build a
generative World model or a predictive
World model that's very surprising I
should probably explore that
um and so of course I'm condensing the
concept down into sort of like the
exploration part of the explore exploit
trade-off and that I know you know but
uh that characterizes reinforcement
learning so that's just what we mean
when we say epistemic or epistemic
foraging and obviously of the ramen
foraging you know can be likened to what
the ants are doing right they're
exploring their environment
and so I guess with that in mind so that
way everyone's sort of on the same page
here uh to get to your question about
the differences about how does this work
versus like your typical neural based
approaches to active inference in I
would fall into that category of oh I
build neural models biological process
models uh those are very much focused
you could say at the individual level at
least the ones that I am aware of when
you're building for example even a back
propagation based uh partially
observable Markov decision process in uh
you know active inference that's like a
single agent right you're trying to
build this construct that is trying to
you know balance the epistemic quantity
with its instrumental term which by the
way another jargon term for you of the
ramen and Travis that's just like your
reward signal or your prior preference
or a prior distribution over goal States
and so the agent these agents sort of
like deal with that trade-off but at an
individual agent level now again I'm
sure there's an interpretations of these
from other perspectives
the ant-based approach even though I
would not argue per se that this has at
least an explicit form or a connection
at least that Bob the ramen has made
clear to active inference but the idea
is that this is like a multi-agent
approach to active inference and so the
ants when they conduct their epistemic
forging which arguably is a very very
simple model each and each Anton of
themselves is you know essentially a
bunch of you know coefficients and some
hard-coded rules uh because they're uh
their job is essentially to work
together with their pheromone trails to
figure out oh what parts of the
superstructure are useful so I'd say
that that's different and it lends
itself in some ways of course you can
make the ants more complicated and lose
the benefit I'm just about to say you
could massively parallelize this and
this is one of those key strengths that
I think is natural in for example a lot
of actually transpired optimization
algorithms and and Colony optimization
is one of them is you know Abdul ramen's
been using hundreds of CPUs and you can
put these ants on their own individual
processor and the communication that's
you know occurring across them as they
exchange information
is you know through the pheromone Trails
there's an indirect mechanism it's not
terribly complex to facilitate and I'm
sure that there's even better ways to go
about doing like asynchronous forms of
communication and further further
optimizes I Know Travis and Travis can
add to this has done things on like
citizen science and uh distributed
computing through you know the you know
volunteer volunteer Computing and how
you can distribute this through a
massive Global asynchronous Network so
you can imagine adapting the uh ant form
sorry the ant colony optimization
approach to some like distributed
massively distributed version of active
inference where you essentially have to
write down that the variational free
energy and I'm I'm putting quotes around
this because again there is no concrete
term written in out the ramen's work I
mean because we haven't at least we
haven't viewed this from the active
inference perspective directly each ant
is optimizing its own variational free
energy but then there's probably a
global quantity that sort of is really
as a function of those pheromone trails
in the individual hand agents
um and then of course with the
exploitation term or the instrumental or
the uh you know what is the reward
signal to give an RL term that's sort of
driven by the performance of the actual
agent on the each candidate agent on the
task right of the ramen you compute like
mean squared error when you're doing
time series predictions so in some sense
we have built-in you know uh a reward
function that we use and again for those
in the active inference group here you
know you can use the complete class
theorem and look at you know the prior
preferences saying oh well the reward is
actually technically a prior preference
right it's like a log probability so
with that in mind you could squint at
and Colony optimization and I guess the
big benefit comes from that massive
parallelization that you wouldn't
actually very easily if at all get with
you know our single agent neural based
approaches
um and that might be an interesting
place to build on and I'll stop rambling
at this point I'm not sure if that was
helpful
that that was awesome even earlier today
Chris fields in the physics as
information processing course was
talking about the classical information
inscribed on the blanket which is like
the pheromone perception and deposition
pheromone modification and and
perception sense making an action which
we can associate with like the nest mate
cognitive system so then there could be
as simple as a pass-through for the nest
mate could be any arbitrary relationship
described with a blanket simple Nest
mate sophisticated Nest mate
um like another level of Time series
modeling
whereas there's the environmental time
series modeling and that's just in the
ants and then the
um
fourth dimension is like that Quantum
rotation which goes from the lower
dimensional classical stigmergic screen
into the quantum informational space and
so that's one of the discussions on
going in octinf right now is about well
previous approaches to connect Quantum
formalisms to
macro let's just say neural phenomena
based it upon the plausibility of like a
molecular electronic
bubbling up whereas just with research
from decision making and statistics and
just multi-perspectival modeling and all
the issues associated with the
physicalities information transfer the
finiteness of it
the quantum formalism becomes useful
just by itself with or without Reliance
on some other
electronic phenomena so it's just a lot
of very interesting connections like
having the degrees of freedom on the
blanket which could be noiseless and
four bits or it could be noisy with this
really specific thing but in silico you
get to
play it from both sides and scale things
up and down and do these meta heuristics
on top of that arbitrary space could be
really simple for learning or it could
be however much and and then just like
the ant colony algorithm is is
ultimately Federated through embodiment
that property makes it a really useful
candidate for biomimetry so a lot of
times when people think about collect
Behavior they're thinking about like the
flock of birds and the school of fish
and those are of course Collective
systems and Collective behavioral and
all these kinds of like complex systems
properties
can be studied in that type of system
but it is also neglecting it at least an
analytical degree of Freedom with the
stigma G
so that really opens up that both the
quantum the classical information
or both Niche modification and
behavioral uh and cognitive modeling so
just to add on because I think and and
then also what the node is could even be
heterogeneous or unknown or fit in in
different ways or fixed through design
processes so just like the ant colonies
are flexible enabling them to live in
all kinds of places make all these kinds
of nested decisions to interact with
each other
that that flexibility is just like the
tip of the iceberg of what we could even
just describe because there would always
be real environments we hadn't yet tried
with ant colony so we really would never
know the full extent of like all the
repertoire and the Dynamics of the ant
system but then we can just abduct into
new mathematical statistical
distributional Frameworks pull back to
different levels of the learning in The
Meta learning process and just start
there and then um almost ironically or
or um maybe the opposite of that like it
could be applied to ant colony video
data or movement data or foraging
activity itself but
it kind of
takes inspiration and develops in
parallel or in conversation so it's not
like balance what real ants can do or
you could constrain it so that there are
properties that real ants have like they
can only interact with in this certain
way or like there really are only this
many pheromones do model comparison so
it's it's a lot of degrees of freedom I
feel like you all are opening up with
the ant colony modeling and also one of
the challenging pieces of multi-agent
simulation is kind of like the
open-endedness with the design space
so then it's very hard for even creative
ideas like sometimes to find the right
compute resources that that obviously
are still even needed for for what you
discovered
um with the analysis here an awesome
question from Bert in the chat I just
wanna I just want to clarify just so uh
make sure that I got the right term and
certainly Abdullah Ramen and Travis you
might want to look it up is when you
were saying blanket you were referring
to a Markov blanket correct yes so the
technical definition of Markov blanket
is when you have a Bayesian graph where
nodes are the variables and edges are
relationships amongst these variables
for any given node of Interest we'll
just call it internal States so these
are not features of the world it's not
tagged on to some tissue of a real Nest
mate in the world this is something
that's tagged onto or like a perspective
we could take on any node in a base
graph and then all the nodes that
insulate it in the co-parents are known
as the blanket in the sense that it's
like one layer insulator and there's a
lot of more discussion on it and the
philosophical implications and all these
generalizations of that
but broadly the Markov blanket is just
the inbound dependencies which we
associate with sense making and
perception learning attention and then
the outgoing dependencies for the agents
which we associate with like action
influence in
some Downstream pointing way
thank you I just wanted to clarify that
because I don't think Abdul Rahman and
Travis might be familiar just with that
terminology it's very uh forstonian you
know very active inferency kind of
jargon so I wanted to make sure that
they got that from the physics point of
view thanks yeah yeah totally great
point and um
ask a question now from bird supper says
very impressive solving generative
models with more generative models
sounds very promising what about
replacing ants with convolutions
I'd like a meta learning algorithm like
having a neural networks that learns how
to optimize your other neural networks
yeah I mean this concept I think is is
interviewed at some point I mean in
machine regular but we we wanted to
apply for nature based uh method that
mimics like the the mother nature which
is the uh you know uh nature is the most
efficient optimization Revolution system
so
um looking at the results that we could
that are there in those nature implying
nature based methods uh they were
Superior to any other method
um and the results we got also which
just pointed out that pointed that out
that we so good performers are coming
out from these results from our results
and previous results from other methods
as well
so so I hop in here a little a little
bit too
um in the case of neural architecture
research there's kind of a couple
classes of approaches all right one is
constructive so kind of like where we
build larger and larger networks and try
and keep your network size as minimal to
try and find your optimal solution other
types of neural architecture search
approaches use like a superstructure and
this is kind of how the the earlier
iterations of this were where you have a
bound of your search space and you try
and find the optimal Network within that
bound so one is like trying to build
things from the ground up and the other
one's trying to like trim down a big
Network to a small Network
um ask your question about convolutions
there's a type of there's been a fair
bit of research lately in what's called
graph based neural networks which can
which can use convolutions over like a
discrete Graph Search space and can
potentially produce other graphs and I
believe there's been some neural
architect architecture search work using
this but one of the main
and I think cool things about the
approach here which is different from
those is that even if you have a graph
based neural network and you have your
search base
um defined as some kind of Matrix where
things are off and on depending on which
nodes are connected to each other you
have a fixed search space which may not
be big enough or it might be not not be
the correct search space for this neural
architecture search problem where this
method here is all continuous right so
um within this continuous search space
you really have it gives the algorithm a
lot of freedom maybe too much freedom
but um a really open-ended way of
generating a wide variety of neural
architectures which if you pre-constrain
your algorithm to work within a fixed
discrete superstructure you may not even
find them because they're not even in
they're not even a possibility
so that's one of the reasons we didn't
we didn't go that route but there there
are graph based neural artistic
architecture search algorithms out there
where basically you take the
architecture as a graph you
um train a neural network to spit out
another graph that it might think is
better
and those use convolutions sometimes
that helps
that's awesome so convolution sounds
like yes um and one thought on that is
yes the ants solve all these incredible
patterns and and
kind of do amazing things amidst
informational and physical limitations
like like we all do
um
having the ants be able to
just
make trade-offs
within a task space
and then have a dial as modelers to make
that task space kind of like touching
the pheromone distribution
or metacognitive ants and all or
something emulating essentially that
um and for example the octave inference
forward-looking and like thinking
through other Minds
that there could be a kind of cognitive
colony
so then that enables in silico
total thought experiment colonies
and through data driven processes also
kind of keep continuity with that model
perhaps literally continuity with the
model and then connected to empirical
which is something that that
um
is very hard for agent-based modeling
which as you kind of Point into often
sets certain fixed axes performs like a
sweep
looks at one mechanism doesn't look at
all these possible mechanisms of like
learning and intra and intergenerational
and all these time effects
so how do you see this being used in
different research or application
domains
wow
well I mean we were the main use case
that we're thinking of was new
revolutionary architecture search uh
it's for to apply it for other domains
other than your Arctic search we didn't
figure out that yeah uh I think Alex can
explain on that
I can hop in a little bit too I mean so
basically this this type of algorithm if
you need to generate graphs
and you don't necessarily have a fixed
structure for that graph and when I say
graph I mean like a computer science
graph where you have nodes images
um so pretty much anything involving
graph construction I think these types
of methods no no that works kind of
under the hood are you know can be
represented as graphs and usually are so
I think we're using it for neural
networks because it's really popular but
um you know there's other other
algorithms out there like you know the
traditional uh traveling salesman
um there's like routing problems all
that any type of stuff where you might
need to generate a graph
in a smart way let's go do that yeah
take another point though I think what's
really cool here and I don't want to
steal up around those Thunder but you
know his last point on future direction
is
um while the a particular version of
this ant colony optimization search is
running to find an optimal neural
network a colony has fixed parameters
that it operates Within but if you think
of the colony as an organism as opposed
to the ants being an organism you can
evolve colonies that optimize how it the
the ants themselves act so you can have
evolving colonies that in a smaller
sense also evolve or optimize what
they're doing within their prescripted
uh parameters for the agents they're
generating so you can have like a Meta
Meta accuracy is really cool it's
awesome I mean The evolutionary account
of of a why question for amp Behavior
today one part of that answer is like
because colonies That Couldn't under
that regularity or constraints survive
we've had a long long time to wipe those
off the table and so every biological
system has to have that kind of
multi-scale ordering
um in 2021 we made the active infra ants
paper which was modified from an
epistemic foraging visual attention task
um
about scanning around and then learning
a cicade policy that had to do with
epistemic foraging but not leaving the
trace and then the main modification to
bring that active inference epistemic
visual foraging model into the active uh
inference ant setting was to add a
pheromone rule just like you described
even though of course again that's not
the only pheromone rule but that's just
the most simple pheromone rule that we
can generalize from as you definitely
have and there are just many emerging
ways of of modeling those multi-scale
active inference models so composing
across layers which we might associate
more with the kind of laterality
of things that happen through
interactions and then also as Mike Levin
shows with kind of the time Diamond
systems that have a memory retention
components
of some shape cognitive shape and then a
pro tension
um awareness or agency or other
attributes you can use to describe that
and that that's a statistically amenable
way to describe things
and then there's a variety of
implementations on a given statistical
problem or like Federated compute
architecture it might be the case that
you're not running like the pure Matrix
multiplications that are shown in like
the early Matlab code of active
inference different components of
machine Learning Systems might be kind
of composed together also ways uh kind
of abiding by those patterns of
communication but then there's a level
of abstraction that that um we can still
describe but it doesn't mean active
inference is going to be like kind of
causing it
so that's what gives a lot of
flexibility and it's really cool that
through your backgrounds Alexander and
work and and these kinds of
collaborations that like the active
inference perspective on multi-agent
modeling with all these other views can
at least come together
um
comparatively
and then that is gonna I think be quite
an interesting Interchange to apply this
entire
tissue type or Colony type
thinking up above and within the models
just a lot of degrees of freedom like
you said could be too much I mean and I
think there's different ways to I think
you depends on how you want to take the
ant metaphor and you know again it's
it's kind of interesting some of the
questions or comments that you're making
Daniel and some from the audience about
you know uh how does this you know think
about it from a cognitive point of view
I mean I do work in cognitive
architectures of course again kind of
from the whole single agent you know or
single entity and you know modeling a
single brain in its different regions
but I think if you take you know a
nature inspired uh optimization approach
like the ant metaphor that Abdel Ramen
uh you know you know latched on to and
that's sort of like the way in which he
formalizes how or it takes a principle
of how ants interact with their world
interact with each other uh and then you
know mathematically model those
particular Concepts step by step
I think if you bend the metaphor and say
well okay could the ant colony metaphor
apply to multi-human agent systems right
or other entities does it does it does
the ant necessarily can it be
generalized Beyond you know the physical
creature upon which uh abdulrahman based
his initial metaphor and that's an
interesting philosophical kind of take
to it and then how do you apply that to
let's say building a multi-agent
cognitive system and then of course says
Travis was discussing with you and you
were mentioning metacognition and you
know you could think of ant colonies of
ant colonies but you could even replace
the word ant and just say well we have
you know clusters of you know
intelligent agents or however whatever
degree of modeling we're doing because
again I do want to emphasize that at
least they can'ts and ants agents that I
have worked with in the context of the
ramen you know they are not in each and
of themselves even I would argue if
nothing else a very extremely simplified
generative model or a very very very
simple control system there's no neural
network under each one because then
you'd have to simulate computationally
each one of these ants within the
framework so I think there's always that
good practical machine learning kind of
viewpoint of well you know there's
always a how do you simulate that in you
know obvious working with CPUs it's not
like he has an army of gpus to replace
them with convolutional networks again
if you have the resources this would be
awesome but uh you know expense and
money is another constraint on this
planet but
um I think there's interesting views and
interesting directions one could go by
taking inspiration from the ant metaphor
and you know the concept of pheromones
and translate them to other you know
other real world signals and how for
example communication patterns among you
know other animal entities or other
human agents and I think that that opens
up an interesting perspective and if
you're constantly trying to connect it
back to you know free energy
minimization and trying to say well how
are we balancing you know the terms that
you can decompose it into an epistemic
and an instrumental and how are these
balancing out and how how are these
physical processes that we specify uh
you know balancing those terms that's
just a very interesting place to be and
you mentioned you know active inference
versions of ants and that's fascinating
and of itself uh last comment I have is
again the degree of modeling and what
you are modeling like if you're modeling
a society or organization you know
that's one way you could use you know
the ant colony framework if you will or
optimization or meta heuristic
optimization Frameworks to you know then
cast you know uh you know a system any
type of complex multi-agent system as an
active inference kind of uh you know
engaging uh process or you could go
really low level and think about you
know cells in a body or you know or
units that make up organs or organelles
and trying to say well can we use this
to model that level of granularity
within like a human or an animal entity
right and I think there's some
fascinating questions about how does
this metaphor manifest itself at
different time scales and different
degrees of you know perspective right
about how you're modeling what are you
looking at what's the picture that you
want to emulate and of course there's
always under the hood this practical
consideration of well okay the
computational expense they allocate and
are you able to actually run that
simulation long enough because I think
all the ramen incorrect me if by if I'm
wrong you mentioned like one of the
experiments I think was for the bigger
systems took a month right of course
this was on CPUs uh you know that that
can get pretty uh prohibitive if you
want to go even bigger than that but
again I think it just depends on you
know what Hardware you have to simulate
the Sun yeah yeah and also uh I mean
using high performance Computing is not
always feasible for for smaller um so if
we try to model the brain of ants like
small neural network
um you're using a GPU might not be like
a feasible solution and Travis is the
high performance Computing specialist
here it's expert value but like sending
data to the GPU and getting it back it's
very time consuming and resources can
continue so it will worsen the the the
the the time consumption rather than
solving it because communicating between
the the main memory and the GPU would it
had like a an overhead so it has to be a
big enough problem to actually utilize
this GPU in in such Solutions yeah so
um when you have like you know the super
large language models or large models
for computer vision they do a lot of
just massive operations on tensors which
are basically multi-dimensional matrices
right and when you have really big wide
tensors they you can parallelize the
operation really nicely across the GPU
a lot of this work is based on uh doing
like a Time series forecasting time
series specification on on sensor data I
think stuff from like Power Systems so
you know in the input to a large
language model might be a thousand or
more
um you know word length of a word
embedding which is actually not not huge
but it only if you go up to computer
vision model the input image may be a
thousand five thousand pixels and that
gives you like actually a million inputs
right
um when you're working with sensor
Systems off of aircraft power plants
that type of thing you may have 50 to
100 inputs and when you're working with
this type of Time series data you don't
need a massive super wide neural network
and then if you add in recurrency where
you have to do back problem over time
and over other things like this you
actually can't really parallelize it
nicely on a GPU so for us the CPU is
actually more more efficient we tried
Abdul Rahman wrote a bunch of code a
long time ago to put this stuff on gpus
and we found it was quite a bit slower
so depending on what you're doing with a
neural network a GPU actually isn't the
right answer
um and but the other cool thing about
this which I think does have maybe even
potential for there is that
um you know one of the big not talked
about problems in machine learning is
that back propagation is the fastest
thing we know but it's inherently not
scalable like you can get a bigger
better GPU to do your bits of your
network in parallel to speed things up
but that only gets better if you have a
bigger network if you want to speed up
the training process you can't just add
another CPU or another GPU and make
backdrop go faster you can make the
forward and backward pass through your
neural network faster but you still have
to do but every Epoch of back prop
iteratively
um a method like this where we're
generate we're not we're not one it's
back prop three so it's not using back
prop we can use a nature Inspire or
other method to use hundreds of
computers and you can throw twice as
many computers at it and get a result
twice as that twice as fast whereas that
problem you can't do that so if you
think about actually being able to train
a neural network faster
um that crop actually you know it's got
a pretty pretty low speed limit for for
what we need to do and it's kind of a
big problem with the machine learning
community that people don't like to talk
about because they're like oh I'll just
buy the next big Nvidia GPU and that'll
do things faster
so that
that's super interesting does this maybe
even bring up a kind of relationship
where things like a graphics
visualization of course a GPU does well
and that's like the screen changing
through time with the classical process
that can be massively unfolded
and then the cognitive models ultimately
of the nest mates which which again can
be nested but the cognitive the thing
that's more Quantum more cognitive model
like you can do in parallel
because the minds are not influencing
each other except through stigmergy so
then that is CPU bound the size The
Colony
but um and then you could use different
like Graphics techniques like there are
colonies organisms so one ants being
or or it's a philosophical question what
what is the scale at which uh a exists
but all throughout California with the
Argentine Ant for example and so how do
we deal with those kinds of like mesh
work cognitive systems all the way on
through 50 in an acorn
there's just all these different
trade-offs that are being made and like
in the featureless deserts there's um
different wayfinding pathfinding
um sensor integration polarization of
light like different cognitive
strategies because they might be going
out long distance and dragging something
home not leaving any pheromone because
it's not any more likely to have food
there so in that case the stigma G is
basically minimal to essentially none
and then in other situations you could
have something that's very adherent to
distributions to the point of being like
fit to to very
um like kind of a normative path
but that's happening at a level that
allows the um different compute
architectures
different information architectures
and ultimately different biological
embodiments to to really engage
fruitfully again looking at the
variability the diversity of biological
algorithms for Collective Behavior
which have been studied by Professor
Gordon and others in so many different
angles yet sometimes it can feel like
multi-agent models always start kind of
like at Square One demonstrate some
proof of concept phenomena
and then that is utilized as part of
like a bigger perspective but it's not
like that model was ever like claimed to
have been tuned to maximum performance
it's like well we got decision making
Behavior
you could transfer this to group
decision making with honeybee decision
making or something like that
but
there's still a big gap there
but I think what you're describing with
the cans which is funny because it could
be cannot but also the cans is the
dialect
which is spoken yeah so it was very I
mean we came up with it
great choice and it's just like yeah
because there's multiple perspectives to
swap from on
the classical screen because the meaning
of the word is is something that's
happening that fourth dimension
cognitively
the meaning of the word isn't to be
found just on the blanket just on the
interface itself that's just the
communication
um and that's like a bounded systems and
then if you model a cognitive system
that doesn't have that kind of a
constraint
then so represented by a map that that
has some kind of blanket uh index some
kind of blanketing like if you don't
embody that constraint in the
statistical model the map you're
ignoring one of the fundamental
constraints of modeling
the way that things happen in an
embodied fashion maybe there's some
abstract space for a certain problem
that's just like a total slam dunk
however for for full generality at least
to the space that we know of of
biological life forms and their
engagements and like ecological
um
engagements not just like within one
Behavior just that space is is so vast
and there's so much to learn across
different systems within two again to
abduce away
into different like information
architectures and active inference being
some subsetter type of those
so it's awesome work do you have any
last comments
um I uh well being giving ability to for
friends to be self-aware and well aware
about this environment it's actually
something that we implemented
um in in our last work here with the BP
free accounts
um they are indirectly aware about their
environment and Theory
um adapt adapting to the changes in
their clinical environment by indicted
meaning that they are evolving using a
genetic based algorithm
um to just change their behavior like
how these things the the the word the
word the pheromones when they take the
steps and some other times or some other
characters that they have so they are
adapting but kind of like nuts in
um an intelligent uh uh way but through
it through through Evolution if you want
to say actually we we consider putting a
putting a brain in each one of these
agents but then again as
design because we couldn't like paralyze
that it will take time to train each one
of these brains as we evolve the neural
networks
awesome
Alexander or Travis any last thoughts
oh okay
um
jeez I I I'm just really really happy I
mean I think this this work is really
interesting and it opens up a lot of
um pretty cool Avenues again
if we can get to the point where we're
evolving colonies that are producing
ants
um and can see where that can go so one
of the big issues in neural architecture
search is the whole question of what is
an optimal neural network and what an
optimal neural network is
um could be different for well will be
different for different tasks but not
only that even if it's the same data set
how you're using that neural network
could lead to less optimal lesser more
optimal neural network right depending
on doing with it maybe you need one
that's more energy efficient maybe you
don't care about energy efficient
efficiency or performance and you'll
take a slower neural network but you
need more accuracy so being able to have
algorithms which can automate this whole
process for us and tune them to what we
actually want to use the neural network
for is really important and I think one
just having ant colony optimization be
able to optimize the network for a
problem was great but two if we can make
it such that the algorithm itself is
self-optimizing it really can streamline
this whole process where right now if
you're doing machine learning it can be
kind of miserable you like make a neural
network architecture you try it out see
how well it does oh nope that didn't do
do so well let me tweak a couple knobs
um automating that process my whole life
as a computer scientist is about being
lazy about being smart about it so
whatever I can optimize so that I don't
have to do it over and over again seems
like a good good use of my time so I'll
be smart about having to do as little as
possible in the future
then I guess uh my I don't have too much
to add to that I think uh a lot of the
good discussion has happened already and
we talked about various implications and
ways of viewing you know and Colony
optimization from you know other
perspectives including an active
inference point of view so I guess
really more from a closing thought on my
end is that uh it will be interesting or
it is an interesting direction to think
about like I said earlier or suggested
about the adaptation of the metaphor
right to other systems and what are you
trying to model and you know what's your
goals from a scientific and
philosophical point of view what are
what are the questions you seek to
answer and I think it might be very
interesting again given other
developments and you know Computing
technology uh in ways in which you
implement the parallelization that I
think is That's What attracted me the
most to a lot of these meta heuristic
algorithms even things like particle
swarm and you know when I worked with
Travis many years ago on the exam
algorithms you saw our names on that and
uh working on that type of stuff the
part that always caught my attention is
again that ability to say I can put
these entities on different you know
processing Computing processing you know
resources or devices and then they will
interact or interact and exchange their
results in some way to try to optimize
uh some you know often complex
multi-objective cost function and so I
think the part that we'll see or that
would encourage the wider spread
adoption of even like meta-heuristic
algorithms in general not to say that
they aren't used a lot in for example
the engineering domains is again the
development of you know parallel
Computing processing systems and I think
exploiting things like asynchronous
Computing that was again another angle
that caught my attention from Travis you
know he's done a lot of work on you know
genetic optimization in their evolution
from an asynchronous point of view and
how can we allocate whatever resources
are available you know and you know
Distributing them across Global networks
I think that might be the best shot to
scaling up let's see with what we got
right now there might be again you've
mentioned annual Quantum technology
Quantum Computing is another interesting
place that sort of like changes the game
um uh but you know barring you know
technologies that we don't necessarily
have exactly at their best at this
moment you know how can we take
advantage of Citizen citizen science or
distributed computing or peer-to-peer
type of communication and building
massive active inference systems that
you know embody like the multi-agent
metaphor of and Colony optimization or
other nature inspired Frameworks and
um Can this system you know evolve over
very long spans of time just like
Evolution really worked another piece my
final count and uh is that uh why I'm
interested sometimes in evolution is
that to me it is the inductive bias that
provided us with structures that allow
for example a human agent babies can you
know to operate already babies can
already recognize faces right and uh we
we have certain instinctual reactions
and certain mechanisms that
evolutionists endowed us with and so a
fascinating question is what is the
interplay of this you know the idea of
simulating an artificial form of
evolution maybe building you know DNA
structures are very very simplified
computational structures which would
answer Abdel rahman's concern about well
maybe we don't want the agents to be too
smart and of themselves because I can't
really simulate that unless you give me
like a decade to run the simulator
um but you could maybe come up with a
more fundamental primitive and then use
that as a starting point for your neural
network let's say Daniel you're you want
to do some task in image segmentation
and and you know like okay but what can
uh your evolutionary framework give me
well I'll say here here's a template to
start from this is this is a kernel on
which you build your framework and you
know it's like a DNA structure and this
has evolved across you know many many
years of distributed peer-to-peer
Computing and you can imagine building
this Mammoth evolving continual learning
style you know evolutionary algorithm
whether it is based on uh genetic
algorithms brand colony and you could
imagine that might be an interesting way
to think about it and by the way I am
spitballing and generating an idea of
like how I could Envision a scalable
form without inventing a new Computing
system that I don't know will or will
not exist uh because Quantum has a lot
of problems still to solve too like
super conducting there's super
temperatures or trapping photons as I
have learned
um so that might be an interesting
Direction and I think the scaling of
this especially from the Practical end
is going to be the most important we're
going to need to pull together all the
tools that we have as I mentioned before
so I'll stop there too because I'll end
up rambling more so hopefully that made
sense
well this was very epic and inspiring so
good luck with the work you're all
welcome to suggest uh another
piece that we might focus on or or
continue the discussion however you see
fit because it's super interesting
Direction so thank you until next time
thank you so much bye